- Hey folks, and welcome to the lesson
on building your design gut instinct.
So I work with a lot
of beginning designers
through this course and one thing
I hear again and again is like,
Eric I don't have a
gut instinct for design
and this complaint comes in
a couple of different forms.
Some people say, oh, I know what I like
but I just can't create it.
I know what's good design,
I know what's a beautiful
site when I see it.
But the moment I opened
up Figma or sketch,
I just can't make it for
myself, I'm out of ideas.
I don't know what's going to help me.
That's one style of this
no gut instinct problem.
The other one is some people say,
I don't even know what looks good.
Like I don't even know what good design is
and whether you fall into
one camp or the other,
I think it's a similar root problem.
It's not having a gut instinct for design.
And so in this lesson,
I want to talk about
a simple two-step process
that will help you
build your design gut instinct.
But before we do that,
just consider for a second.
What does it mean to have a
gut instinct for something?
I think in the mind of a
beginner, when you see a problem
a lot of times your brain
just becomes flooded
with possible solutions.
So I have this design, it
looks bad, how do I fix it?
Maybe I have to change the color.
Maybe I have to change the font.
Maybe I have to change the sizing.
Maybe I need to make something bigger
or smaller or have more
space or less space
or maybe I need to use
a better vertical rhythm
using a baseline grid
based on the golden ratio.
There's some blog posts
that could tell you that,
that's not the answer though.
What you need is a design gut instinct.
So that instead of hearing
all these different ideas
come rushing into your head,
you only have a couple solutions
but any of those solutions
has an unreasonably
high chance of working.
That's what it's like when you
have a design gut instinct.
You have just a couple
solutions come into your mind
but any of them could be
unreasonably effective.
So that's the end goal.
That's what we want to get to.
How do we get there?
Let's talk about it.
In order to start talking about building
your gut instinct for design, we're going
to go all the way back to the very first
professional design project that I did.
Yes, that's right folks.
You are looking at the monstrosity
that is the first design
I got paid to create.
And you know what, I'll
be the first to admit.
It's really bad.
If you look here, there's so many things
that I could call out that are wrong.
I mean, we're just starting
at the top and this button,
which is sadly cut off because I think
there was some other junk up here
that didn't make any sense.
This button is basically the color
of puke for no good reason at all.
And then it's on top of this kind of muddy
toxic sludge sort of
color that if you look
at the vast majority of
professional designs,
you will not see using
anything even remotely similar
to this color as a theme color.
And then we have this
weird crosshatched pattern
which doesn't really add to
the overall design in any way.
And then we switched
gears with the colors.
We go for a nice peach search bar
that remains utterly unaligned
with any of the elements around it.
It's at once awkwardly long
and yet not so long enough
that it aligns with the
rest of the content.
Then we switch color gears again
and we go with full on completely bright
rich blue, red, and green, and
probably default CSS colors
before going back to puke
for a couple of links.
And then we bounce over to blue here.
And of course, I mean
the background colors
don't make any sense either.
It's sort of a slight blueness to this
whereas this is a flat gray.
Then we have the crosshatching.
I could go on and on
like this is real bad.
I could rip it apart all day.
That's not really the point,
that's not what we're here for.
What I want to say though,
when I was designing this,
it was not like I tried on this.
I tried and I probably tried for 10
or 20 hours to get this
page looking as good
as I could and you know
what, I couldn't (laughs).
The problem was as a beginner,
I had all these ideas
about what to change.
I had all these ideas and
yet I didn't actually know
which ones would yield good
results or yield bad results.
I didn't have a gut instinct for design.
So what I needed to do is
follow this two step process
for building a design gut instinct.
Step one, find a design that looks good.
This is actually the simple part
but just a couple of notes here.
One is you're always going
to have some designers
who don't think that a
particular design looks good.
That's fine.
When I say find a design that looks good,
just find one that like
overall, you kind of
have this gut sense that like,
yes, this is a good design.
Maybe it was designed by
a professional designer
who really knows what they're doing
or maybe you just know that you like it
and hey that's good enough.
If you really like something like,
okay we're going to call
it design that looks good.
Now the second step is
really the important one.
It's to analyze why the design is good.
And you're gonna hate me for saying this
but what I want you to
actually do is write
out a list of why you think
a particular design is good.
This is sort of the level of
analysis that I want you to do.
And the reason why is
because when you force
your brain to come up
with a name for something,
or to describe something,
you're forcing your brain to
have like a little connection
or make a kind of a connection point
that you can then latch
to an other designs.
So let's actually take
a look at this in action
because it's seeming kind
of abstract right now.
So here's this site, it's
for an app called photon.
The site is in Figma and you
can open up the Figma file.
I have it linked below.
I don't believe the site
is live at this point
but I will post it if I see it.
Anyhow, it's a site that is like
kind of scroll through it here.
It looks good.
This is a well-designed site.
Now, like I said of course
there could be some designers
who see this and go like,
no, I don't like it.
They're going to be some
people who think it's too plain
or whatever, but for the most part
I think most of us can generally
agree, this looks good.
This looks awesome.
It's clean, simple, it's friendly.
It's colorful, whatever.
It's better than some geo
cities page from back the day.
And that's kind of just the baseline level
that we're looking for.
Now, that's step one.
We found a design that looks good.
Step two is we're going to analyze it.
And like I said, we're
going to make a list
of things that make this design good.
The reasons could be vague.
They could be articulate.
They could be trivial.
They could be really
serious and important.
It doesn't really matter.
It's just something, just
something for our brains to latch
onto that we can make connections
with other designs and make
connections to our own work.
Now, to be clear, you don't actually
need fancy design terminology
when you're making this list.
I don't need to say, oh I really love
the isometric illustrations.
Like I don't need to know these
are called isometric illustrations.
I love how these isometric
illustrations are used
as a motif across different
areas of the page.
I actually didn't even notice
that until right now they are.
They're all 3D.
You could just be like,
the 3D effect is cool.
That's it.
That's all you need to do.
You just, and as long as your brain
kind of remembers what this 3D
effect is, that's good to go.
You'll undoubtedly see it at
some other site in the future.
You might think it's cool again, there.
You might start to store it
as kind of a little trick for something
that you could do to
make a design look cool
in certain scenarios and there you go.
Likewise, I don't need to know
that this is a probably a
grotesque or a geometric font
a bold geometric or
grotesque headline font.
Don't really need all that terminology.
I could just say I like
the clean font, sans serif
maybe I noticed sans serif
used for the headline.
It just looks neat, clean
and simple and that's it.
That's all I need to say.
The idea here is just that you describe
something that you like
and you kind of attach it
to some reason why you
think it works here.
Now what I'm going to have
you do is pause this video.
And in just a sec, and I'm
gonna have you write down
a list of the reasons
why this is a good site.
So you can just go ahead
and open it and Figma,
if you have it, otherwise
you're just going to open
it in the web viewer.
It's linked below, but go and scroll
through the site and see
what you like about it.
Just take a peak and we'll
start in just a second.
Now I'm going to go over my list.
I'm going to go over what I saw
in this site that I really liked.
This is what I wrote down
because I actually did this exercise.
First thing I said is I love
all of this white space.
There's so much white space in the design.
It just overall, it feels
very, very clean right
between this button and
the next text element.
There are 600 pixels of white space.
That's a lot.
And even between this little divider line
and here there's 200 pixels of white space
someone broke open a
CSS file and wrote, yup.
I want 200 pixels of white space here.
And overall it works
really beautifully well.
I also wrote down that I
really liked the colors.
They feel very fresh and fun
and actually into the color unit
and the lesson called secondary UI colors.
We call color palettes that look like this
where they're very light, cheerful colors.
We call it a playful palette.
And it's one of the five
most common palettes
that I've seen and the only reason
that I bothered to name it
is because I've analyzed
the color of so many apps.
So many little palettes
where you say, okay
kind of a red that borders on pink
and then a blue that leans
more towards aqua or teal.
Like that's a pattern that
I see again and again.
And so I'm going to come
up with a name for it.
And I came up with the
name playful palette.
You don't have to have that name.
You could have some different name.
You could have just said,
they're playful colors.
They're fun colors.
They're light colors.
It doesn't matter.
You just get your brain to recognize, ah
there's something about colors like this.
And maybe I can't describe it yet
but I'm going to see it
enough down the road.
I can figure out exactly
what it works for and why.
Another thing I said is I said
the layout feels really impactful
and about the impactful bit,
I really meant it for kind of this area
above the fold here, before
I've started scrolling.
I just have this sense of like the text
on the left with this big
image on the right here.
Just makes it look well, I mean impactful
I guess that's the word I chose
and it's not like I really
have an exact definition
of what that word means.
And probably before I was a designer
I would never actually have even said,
oh that it has an impactful layout.
But the whole idea is if I
force myself to try and say,
yeah there's something about
having this large image
on one side and then some texts
on another side that just feels
kind of boom in your face.
Well, then I can recognize that pattern
in other places that I see it.
So here's an example.
This is a design template called Cremia.
And if I scroll down a little bit,
okay it's a nice site.
It kind of has this gray scale
with a little bit of
almost gold color scheme
looks nice, looks nice.
And then when I get down
here, I'm like, you know what?
This actually feels kind of impactful too,
have the same text on the left here
of this giant image floating on the right.
This feels really nice.
And it's kind of for the same reason
it's kind of that same
impactful style layout.
And this is just one example
of where I saw something
forced myself to describe it in one place.
And when I see it somewhere
else, I can start to
kind of connect those
ideas and draw a pattern.
And again, the words
here are so important.
If you force yourself
to come up with a word
or a concept to surround the things,
then we're kind of forcing
our brain to recognize that pattern.
And as it becomes a familiar pattern,
then it will eventually
become like gut instinct.
So yes, I get it.
Language is weird and
it's imprecise impactful.
Doesn't really even mean anything
but like use the words
anyways, make up an expression.
It doesn't matter using the same language
for something builds those patterns.
Now there's actually
technically a third step
to this two-step process,
which is to catalog it.
If you find something that you like
and you've analyzed why you like it
you should probably also keep it for later
but we're really not going
to cover that too much.
We're actually going to talk about
that more later on in this unit.
The only other things I want to hit
for now are just two other ways
of kind of looking at this concept.
First of all, I want to say that,
yes you're going to get
a lot of mileage out
of saying why you like a design.
One little variation on that
is to try and decide what
would ruin this design.
If I like it now, what would
cause me to not like it?
And so in the case of me
liking the impactfulness
of this layout, I think one thing
that would cause me to not like it is
if this image over here
was like way smaller.
So maybe I could duplicate this image
and then crop it a little bit here.
This is just going to
take some do in one sec
I'm going to shrink it quite a bit
throw it off to the side and put a layer
of white there so that the
background is kind of hidden.
And there we go.
You know what I was right?
This does not look as good.
It does not look as impactful.
So that's just kind of like
a two or one level trick.
As you're going through
and analyzing what you like
and why, also try and figure out
what would cause you to not like it.
Because if you can make the
design such that it looks worse
you might have a better
idea of why it looks better.
And similarly, instead
of just finding the sites
that you think are really
great and analyzing those
you can also look at sites
that you know are just awful.
So like here's an example,
this is an old geo cities page.
And in some sense it kind
of has the same layout.
There's like text on the left here.
There's an image on the right.
The image is really big.
It could be impactful, but it
doesn't quite hit the mark.
Instead there's like all
kinds of crazy stuff going on.
There's all these stars
which I don't really
know why they're there.
And it looks like the image
was just paste it onto this background.
is really poorly cut
out from its background.
And then we have the
default font, which I guess
in the nineties, that was
really all you had access
to on the web, but whatever
it doesn't look very good.
And then the translation
in English has exactly
the same sort of weight
as the French translation.
So it's really, your
eye doesn't really know
what to make out of these two things
but then you get over to this side
and we introduced two new colors
nowhere else in the design
do you see red or green
and we just kind of have this
like Christmas tree theme
for no reason whatsoever.
Well, geez, that was a lot,
but like the more we can take a look
at something that had
the power to be impactful
but it kinda missed because
it used this default font
and it really didn't draw my eye
towards one or the other
of these translations.
And it's tucked all the
way up in the corner here.
And it has just a really
low quality imagery
in the background, it's like, okay,
I guess all those things matter.
If we're going to make a
good version of this page
we could do it, but those would
all be things we'd probably want to fix.
So one thing that can be
really worthwhile here
is then comparing bad and
good designs side-by-side.
So if we go back to this very first
open include design that I did way back
in the day and we look at how bad it is.
Okay, fine like fun to laugh
at this, but let's actually
find a really good looking
design that's similar.
One that I just pulled
up is one of the top
dribble results for chart.
It is Robo advisor web
app by Michael Parulski.
And if I just kind of
scroll through this and look
at this design, it seems like
everything that I did wrong
in my own chart, he did
so much better in this.
So, whereas here I have these
ugly kind of pukey colors.
He just uses this very nice blue
and look how tastefully
it appears in this button.
And it appears in this
little trend line here.
And it appears even just
slightly in this background.
It's like a very, very
light de-saturated version
of the blue, but you can tell it's kind
of the same color it's going on here.
It's going on here, these
strategies by the way
we're going to talk about
this in the color unit
and how variations on a color is like one
of the most important things
you can be able to do here.
And then, I really botched
the alignment here.
This just doesn't look good.
Like I said, in the charts
and data visualization lesson
we're going to talk about how
to align charts much better.
And he's actually doing it
in a very smart way here.
Everything remains just
feeling super clean
and crisp and even where
my overall layout kind
of has like an awkward
sidebar budding directly up
against this, which has no margin here.
And then there's this other
thing budding straight up
against that with no white space.
His overall layout is like
kind of this two by two grid.
There's these card elements,
the left-hand column is not very wide.
The right-hand main content is much wider.
There's this sidebar in this top nav
with kind of an overall,
very similar styling.
Like everything just is consistent
and laid out super, super well.
And that's really all
there is to it folks.
That is how you build
your design gut instinct.
So I'm gonna send you
out into the wide world
of the web and the apps on your phone
and I'm gonna have you
start analyzing designs.
This is your homework.
I know you've probably
gotten a little spoiled
there hasn't been so much
homework yet and ends now.
So you're going to go out there,
you're going to find great designs.
You're going to figure
out why they're great.
And then you're going to come back
and post you're going to say
why these designs work so well.
You can read other people's submissions
and get some feedback on yours,
but just kind of start
this lifelong process
or career long process of
analyzing why designs work
what you like about them,
and then trying to bring some
of those own tips, tricks,
strategies into your own designs.
So also for your viewing
pleasure, I have included a bunch
of the top design sites that
I often go to for inspiration.
They're all linked below.
You can check out those
or if there's other sites
that you know, you really like,
go look at those first, kind of mix it up
and do your own thing and
really kind of follow your heart
and what you think looks good.
But if you want a couple
suggestions, I've got them below.
So that's everything, we'll
see you in the next video.